Guide to the Fred Turner Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Fred Turner papers
1968-2011
SC1146
Turner, Fred.
6.5 Linear feet 4 cartons, 1 box
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
Fred Turner is an Associate Professor in the Department of Communication at Stanford University and Director of Stanford’s Program in Science, Technology, and Society. He is the author of From Counterculture to Cyberculture: Stewart Brand, the Whole Earth Network, and the Rise of Digital Utopianism (University of Chicago Press, 2006) and Echoes of Combat: The Vietnam War in American Memory (Anchor/Doubleday, 1996; 2nd ed., University of Minnesota Press, 2001). He has just finished drafting a prequel to his last book — this time, a history of American multimedia from World War II to the 1960s. It should be published by the University of Chicago Press some time in 2013. Before coming to Stanford, he taught Communication at Harvard’s John F. Kennedy School of Government and MIT’s Sloan School of Management. He also worked for ten years as a journalist. He has written for newspapers and magazines ranging from the Boston Phoenix and the Boston Globe Sunday Magazine to Nature.
Courses taught by Turner include:
Ph.D. Seminars: Media Cultures of the Cold War (Communication 386/Art History 475); Computing and American Culture Since World War II (Communication 320); Critical Studies in New Media: The Politics of Presence (Interdisciplinary Mellon Foundation Seminar)
Mixed Undergraduate and MA-level Courses: Digital Media in Society (Communication 120/220); Digital Journalism (Communication 117/217)
Undergraduate-only Courses: Media Culture and Society (Communication 1B); Reporting and Writing the News (Communication 104)
Scope and Contents
Files consist primarily of research material, manuscripts, and chapter drafts related to Turner's book, From Counterculture to Cyberculture: Stewart Brand, the Whole Earth Network, and the Rise of Digital Utopianism. Other materials include Stanford University Department of Communications files, presentations, and miscellaneous articles and papers.
Access Terms
Brand, Stewart; Global Business Network; Stanford University. Department of Communication.; Communications; Computer networks--Social aspects.; Information technology--History--20th century.; Stanford University--Faculty.
Collection Contents
- Papers, ACCN 2013-037
  - The Emergence of Telecommunities, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - GBN Scenario Book - Decades of Restructuring, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - GBN Articles, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Deeper News Vol. 9 No. 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - GBN Book Club (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - GBN Origins & History, circa 1980s - 2000s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - GBN Newsclippings (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - GBN Principals, Consultants, & Memberships (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Network Packet (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Articles, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - GBN News Manuals/Articles (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - GBN News Manuals/Articles (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The WELL, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The WELL Cont., circa 1980s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Scenario: Planning Community Day, 1996 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - GBN World View Meetings (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Forums & Reviews, circa 2000s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Internet World Stats (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Articles & Papers, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Articles, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dept. of Communication, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Articles from Stanford Special Collections (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Articles & Papers (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Papers & Articles, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letter to Danica Remy, 1996 May 26 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bill's Presentation at Examiner (1 of 2), 1994 Apr 30 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bill's Presentation at Examiner (2 of 2), 1994 Apr 30 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Biosphere 2 Meeting & Address Book, 1990 Sep 13-14 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Thinking Machines Corporation (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Global Business Network (GBN) - Business Plan Draft, 1988 May (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Global Business Network (GBN) - Business Plan Draft - Appendices, 1988 May (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The WELL Packet (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Global Business Network - Business Description (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Thinking Aids, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Notes for Book, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - News Articles, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Papers & Articles on Human Communication, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Articles on the Change of Technology, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Book - Chapter 4 Material (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Notes & A Magazine, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Notes & Correspondence, 2002-2005 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Notes, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Notes, Emails, & Articles, circa 2000s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Meeting Reports, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Deeper News (1 of 2), circa 1980s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - WELL Meetings (2 of 2), circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The WELL - Memberships & Usage Reports (1 of 3), circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The WELL - Memberships & Usage Reports (2 of 3), circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The WELL - Memberships & Usage Reports (3 of 3), circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - NetDays96 - How-To Guide, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Nano Technology (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Nano Technology (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The WELL - Correspondeces (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The WELL - Netview & Conference Info (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Kelly, Kevin (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Gilder (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Dyson (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Cyberthon (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Brockman (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Brockman (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - WIRED (1 of 4) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - WIRED (2 of 4) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - WIRED (3 of 4) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - WIRED (4 of 4) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 5 (1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 5 (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bard, Stewart (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Articles on Rights of the Computer Community (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - GBN 2 (1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - GBN 2 (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Barlow (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Articles on the People Changing the Computer World (1 of 2), circa 1990s-2000s (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Articles on the People Changing the Computer World (2 of 2), circa 1990s-2000s (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - WIRED - A New Media Company, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Barbooks, Richard (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Gore (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Whole Earth Catalog (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Whole Earth Review (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Rheingold, Howard (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Progress & Freedom Foundation (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Hawken, Paul (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Hacker's Conference (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Turner Images for Counter Culture/ New Econ, 2005 Apr 8 (Box 5)
  - Turner with Fix of Photos (Box 5)
  - Turner - Trips Poster (Box 5)
  - GBN - Rio Chama, 1993 (Box 5)
  - USCO Group- 13 Slides of Verbal America Landscapes, 2005 Oct 4 (Box 5)
  - Turner - Whole Earth Catalog (Box 5)
  - Book Graphics - PPL 2 Fixed (Box 5)
  - PCC Photo (Box 5)
  - WEC - Front & Back Covers, 1968 (Box 5)
  - USCO Kinetic Sculptures in Kranz Stita (Box 5)
  - PCC Originals (Box 5)
  - Turner - Whole Manuscript MS World File, 8 Apr. 2005 (Box 5)
  - Turner - Kheel Inw. AIF File, 2006 Jan 6 (Box 5)
  - Shelley Jackson - Patchwork Girl (Box 5)
  - David Frohman - Copyright & John Coate Pics - Sunday Services (Box 5)
  - Stanford Library - Scans of 5pp From WEC II (Box 5)
  - Whole Earth Catalog (Front & Back Cover B&W), 1968 (Box 5)
  - Turner Crowds Track (Box 5)
  - Figtex Photo - John Coate & Cliff Figallo (Box 5)
  - Counter Culture into Cyberculture Files, 2005 Mar 21 (Box 5)
  - IBM Archives Image - Punch Card, 2005 Jun 7 (Box 5)
  - My Docs (Box 5)
  - weird, wer-may85, & wired files, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 5)
  - GBN Pics: War/Gender/Military Syllab. & HUHB Cover Scan (Box 5)
  - Endnote (Box 5)
  - Turner WEC Pages to Descreen, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Bookd Eudera Endiste, 2005 Sep 27 (Box 5)
  - USCO from Tranz - Sci & Tech in Thederri, Kinetic Sculpture, & Fanfeotshek from NY Times Mag, 1968 May 12 (Box 5)
  - Brand @ Trips Fest by Antidony (Box 5)
  - Fuller Images Stanford spec.con. (Box 5)
  - PCC No. 3 - Alta'r Cover, 1975 Jan (Box 5)
  - Scans From N. Murphy & Turner GBN Pics (Box 5)
  - David Frohman Copyright - Pics of J. Coate Sunday Services (Box 5)
  - Cliff in Guat with Agostin, Xoquic & Water - 2 Versions (Box 5)
  - Turner Tech & Culture Cover 46.3 - WELL (Box 5)
  - Book, 2005 Mar 31 (Box 5)
  - Fred Turner MS. - B.b. & Turner Bibliography (Box 5)
  - bootstrapping, onthebus, & wired files, circa 1990s (Box 5)
  - wec-fall69 files, circa 1969 (Box 5)
  - wec-may74 & weird files, circa 1974 (Box 5)
  - Turner - Fuller Pics (Box 5)
  - GBN Media Secret, Dyson, Gildor, GBN (Box 5)
  - Turner - Whole Manuscript (Box 5)
  - GBN Wec Pics - War/ Medic Syllab (Box 5)
  - softtech, spacecolonies, & bootstrap files (Box 5)
  - info for permissions, thealternative, domebookone, stita, wec, and USCO files (Box 5)
  - Brand at New Games - 16 Images (Box 5)
  - Streshinsky Photos, Trip Fest, & Hand Bill (Box 5)
  - Jpegs of Covers of Whole Earth Catalog, CoEvolution Quarterly, & Space Colonies, 2004 Nov 4 (Box 5)
  - Drop City Scans, 2005 May 2 (Box 5)